Guide to the Aaron W. Berg Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Aaron W. Berg Papers,
1848-1977.
Berg, Aaron W., 1903-1978.
2 linear ft (ca. 610 items in 4 boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library,
4079644
Biographical Note
Lawyer and active alumnus of Columbia University (A.B. 1924; LL.B. 1927).
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, memorabilia, and printed materials concerning Berg's lifelong interest in and work for his alma mater. Berg served the University in many capacities such as vice-president and president of the Alumni Association of Columbia College, 1954-1958, and member of the board of directors of the Alumni Federation of Columbia University, 1946-1958. The correspondence deals chiefly with alumni affairs; some of the major correspondents include Harry J. Carman, Lawrence Chamberlain, Frank S. Hogan, Mr & Mrs Richard Rodgers, and Arthur Hays Sulzberger. Among the photographs are two signed by Dwight D. Eisenhower. Also included is a typescript memoir of Berg's three years as a student in the Columbia School of Law (1927). Berg collaborated with three other students on this memoir. Aaron Berg's correspondence with Dwight D. Eisenhower is at the Eisenhower Library. Also included are literary autographs and manuscripts purchased on the Aaron Berg Fund.
Arrangement
Selected materials cataloged; remainder arranged.
Subjects
Columbia College (New York, N.Y.); Columbia University.; Columbia University--Alumni and alumnae--Societies, etc.; Broughton, Rhoda, 1840-1920.; Burke, Thomas, 1887-1945.; Chamberlain, Lawrence H. (Lawrence Henry), 1906-; Columbus, Christopher.; Du Maurier, George, 1834-1896.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.; Heap, Samuel Davis, 1781-1853.; Lang, Andrew, 1844-1912.; Nesbitt, Cathleen, 1888-1982.; Payne, John Howard, 1791-1852.; Pike, James A. (James Albert), 1913-1969.; Rodgers, Dorothy F., 1909-; Rodgers, Richard, 1902-1979.; Sayers, Dorothy L. (Dorothy Leigh), 1893-1957.; Van Doren, Mark, 1894-1972.; Watts-Dunton, Theodore, 1832-1914.; Sulzberger, Arthur Hays, 1891-1968.; Authors, American.; Authors, English.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Tunisia.; Lawyers--United States.; Universities and colleges--United States.; Universities and colleges--New York (State)--New York.; High schools--New York (State)--New York.; Presidents--United States--Election--1960.; Essays.; Financial records.; Memoirs.; Photographs.; Speeches.; Poems.; High School of Commerce--New York (N.Y.).; Nixon-Lodge Campaign, 1960.; Zeta Beta Tau Fraternity.; Consuls.; Lawyers.
Access Restrictions
Available for faculty, students, and researchers engaged in scholarly or publication projects.
Acquisition
07/13/1990 M-90-07-13 Berg, Aaron W. Bequest
04/09/1996 M-96-04-09 9 items by John Howard Payne 6346B (Berg) Purchase
05/27/1998 M-98-05-27 A. Lang letter 6346B(Berg) (Auerbach) Purchase
Bequest of Aaron W. Berg, 1979 & 1980.
Restrictions on Access
Boxes 2-4 of this collection are located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Broughton, Rhoda (Box 1)
  - Burke, Thomas (Box 1)
  - Carman, Harry James (Box 1)
  - Du Maurier, George (Box 1)
  - Hogan, Frank Smithwick (Box 1)
  - Lang, Andrew (Box 1)
  - Nesbitt, Cathleen (Box 1)
  - Payne. John Howard (Box 1)
  - Pike, James Albert (Box 1)
  - Rodgers, Dorothy (Mrs. Richard) (Box 1)
  - Rodgers, Richard (Box 1)
  - Sayers, Dorothy Leigh (Box 1)
  - Sulzberger, Arthur Hays (Box 1)
  - Tyson, Levering (Box 1)
  - Van Doren, Mark (Box 1)
- Series II: Cataloged Photographs
  - Eisenhower, Dwight D. & Harry J. Carman (Box 1)
- Series III: Uncataloged Correspondence
  - Columbia University Alumni Affairs, 1944-1958 (Box 1)
  - Columbia University Alumni Affairs, 1963-1976 (Box 1)
  - Contributions to Columbia University, 1961-1964 (Box 1)
  - Morris Watkins Dinner, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Morris Watkins Fund, 1972-1974 (Box 1)
  - Nixon-Lodge Campaign, 1960 (Box 1)
- Series IV: Subject File
  - Alexander Hamilton Dinner, 1949-1963 (Box 1)
  - Columbia College Alumni Association, Speech, 19 May 1958 (Box 1)
  - High School of Commerce, Speech on 20th Anniversary of Berg's Graduation, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Columbia College Public Relations Committee Report, May 1960 (with related correspondence) (Box 1)
  - Library of Aaron W. Berg: A handlist (Box 2)
  - Watkins, Francis Leslye. "The Viking" (poem) a.ms.s. (Box 2)
  - Zeta Beta Tau Fraternity (Columbia University Chapter) (Box 2)
- Series V: Photograph, Memorabilia, Printed Material
  - Photographs (uncataloged) (Box 2)
  - Memorabilia (Box 2)
  - Printed Materials: Clippings and Periodicals (Box 3)
  - Printed Materials: Books (Box 3)
  - "Three Years at the Columbia University School of Law" t.ms. (bound) by Aaron W. Berg, Thomas Daly, Frank Joseph, and Herbert X. Stern (Box 4)